<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno primo Reginæ Elizabethe At the parliament begonne at Westmynster, the xxiii. of January in the fyrste yeare of the reigne of oure Soueraigne Ladye, Elizabeth by the grace of God, of England, Fraunce and Ireland, Quene, defendoure of the faithe, [et]c. And there proroged tyll the. xxv. of the same moneth, and then and there holden, kept, and continued vntill the dissolution of the same, beyng the eyght day of May, then nexte ensuynge, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
            <title>Public General Acts. 1559-1560. 1 Elizabeth I</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1559</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898997</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1985:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno primo Reginæ Elizabethe At the parliament begonne at Westmynster, the xxiii. of January in the fyrste yeare of the reigne of oure Soueraigne Ladye, Elizabeth by the grace of God, of England, Fraunce and Ireland, Quene, defendoure of the faithe, [et]c. And there proroged tyll the. xxv. of the same moneth, and then and there holden, kept, and continued vntill the dissolution of the same, beyng the eyght day of May, then nexte ensuynge, were enacted as foloweth.</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts. 1559-1560. 1 Elizabeth I</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xii+ leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Jugge and J. Cawood],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1.5.5.9.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Anno primo Reginæ Elizabethe.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, line 6 of title has: January; 1st line of table: 'act restoring'.</note>
                  <note>At least parts of quires A, D-F are by a different printer or compositor, who uses some Whitchurch/Grafton initials and a few criblé initials belonging to J. Kingston--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lincoln's Inn Library, London, England.</note>
                  <note>missing all after B¹.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150878:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO PRIMO REGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAE ELIZABETHE. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>AT THE parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne at Weſtmynſter, the xxiii. of Ianuary in the fyrſte yeare of the reigne of oure So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Ladye, Elizabeth by the grace of God, of England, Fraunce and Ireland. Quene, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doure of the Faithe. &amp;c. And there proroged tyll the .xxv. of the ſame moneth, and then and there holden, kept, and continued vntill the diſſolution of the ſame, beyng the eyght day of May, then nexte enſuynge, were enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as foloweth. Anno. 1.5.5.9.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of John Cawood</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150878:2"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N act reſtoring to the Crowne the aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient iuriſdictyon, ouer the State Eccleſiaſticall &amp; Spirituall, and abolyſhynge all forrayne power repugnaunt to the ſame. Capi. i.</item>
               <item>An act for the vniformitie of common Praier, &amp; Seruyce in the Churche, and thadminiſtration of the Sacramentes. Capi. ii.</item>
               <item>An acte of Recognition the Quenes highnes tytle to the imperial Crowne of this Realme. Capi. iii.</item>
               <item>An act for the reſtitution of the firſt Fruites &amp; Tenthes, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes reſerued <hi>nomine decime,</hi> and of perſonages impropriate to the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Crowne of this realme. Capi. iiii.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Capi. v.</item>
               <item>An act wherby certein offences be made treaſon. Capi. vi.</item>
               <item>An act for the explanacion of the Statute of ſeditious words and Rumors. Capi. vii.</item>
               <item>An acte to reuiue a Statute made in the .xxiii. yeare of the reigne of king Henry theight, touching the conueying of Horſes, geldings, and Mares into Scotland. Capi. viii.</item>
               <item>An act touching Shoemakers and Curryors. Capi. ix.</item>
               <item>An act touching Tanners, &amp; the ſelling of tanned Lether. Cap. x.</item>
               <item>An acte that the cariyng of Leather Tallowe, or rawe H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des out of the Realme for Marchaundize ſhalbe felony. Capi. xi.</item>
               <item>An act limitinge the times for laieng on land Merchaundize fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyond the Seas, and touching Cuſtomes for ſwete wines. Ca. xii.</item>
               <item>An act againſte the deceitfull vſing of Linnen clothe. Ca. xiii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the ſhipping in Engliſhe Botomes. Ca. xiiii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuaunce of the makynge of Wollen clothe in diuers townes in the countie of Eſſex. Cap. xv.</item>
               <item>An acte that tymber ſhal not be felled to make coles for the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Iron. Ca. xvi.</item>
               <item>An act to contynue the act made againſte rebellious aſſembles. Cap. xvii.</item>
               <item>An act for the preſeruation of Spawn and frye of fiſhe. Ca. xvii.</item>
               <item>An act for the continuaunce of certaine Statutes. Cap. xix.</item>
               <item>An act of a Subſedy of Tonnage and Pondage. Capi. xx.</item>
               <item>An act of a Subſedye, and two fyftenes and Tenthes, graunted by the Temporaltie. Ca. xxi.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:150878:2"/>
            <head>An Acte reſtoryng to the Crowne the auncient Iuriſdiction ouer the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall and Spirituall, and abolyſhyng all forreyne power repugnaunt to the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OSTE HVMBLYE</hi> beſeche your moſte crcellent Maieſtie, youre faythfull and obedient ſubiectes, the Lordes Spirituall &amp; Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and the Commons in this your preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled: That where in time of the raigne of your moſt dere Father of worthy memorye Kynge Henry the eyght: dyuerſe good lawes and ſtatutes were made and eſtablyſſhed, aſwell for the vtter extynguiſhement and puttynge away of all vſurped and forreyne powers and aucthorities out of this your Realme, and other your hyghneſſe dominions and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys: as alſo for the reſtorynge and vnytynge to the imperyall Crowne of this Realme, the auncient iuriſdictions, aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſuperiorities, and prehemynences to the ſame of ryght be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longynge &amp; apperteynyng, by reaſon wherof, we your moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; obedient ſubiectes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xxv. yere of the raigne of your ſayd dere father, were continually kepte in good order, &amp; were diſburde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of diuers great and intollerable charges and exactions before that tyme vnlawfully taken and exacted by ſuch forreyne power &amp; aucthoritie, as before that was vſurped, vntyll ſuch tyme as al the ſayde good lawes and ſtatutes by one acte of Parliament made in the fyrſt and ſecond yeres of the raignes of the late kyng Phyllyppe and Quene Mary, your hyghnes ſyſter entytled an Acte repealyng all ſtatutes, articles and prouiſions made agaynſt the Sea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique of Rome, ſynce the .xx. yere of kyng Henry theyght. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ſtablyſhement of all Spirituall and Eccleſiaſticall poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and hereditamentes conueyed to the laytie, were all clearely repealed and made voyde, as by the ſame Acte of repeale more at large doth and may appeare. By reaſon of whiche Acte of repeale, your ſayde humble ſubiectes were eftſones brought vnder an vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped forreyne power and aucthoritie, and yet doe remayne in that bondage to the intollerable charges of your louynge ſubiectes, yf
<pb facs="tcp:150878:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150878:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150878:4"/>
ſome redreſſe (by thaucthoritie of this your hyghe court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with thaſſent of your hyghneſſe) be not had and prouyded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MAY IT THERFORE</hi> pleaſe your hyghneſſe for the repreſſyng of the ſayd vſurped forreyne power, &amp; the reſtoryng of the ryghtes, iuriſdictions, and preheminences apperteynyng to Thimperiall Crowne of this your Realme, that it may be enacted by thauctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of this preſent Parliament, that the ſayd Act made in the ſaid firſt and ſeconde yeres of the raignes of the ſayd late kinge Phillip &amp; Quene Mary, and all and euery braunche, clauſes, and articles therin conteyned (other then ſuch braunches, clauſes, and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as hereafter ſhalbe excepted) may fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the laſt day of this Seſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of parliament, by aucthoritie of this preſent parliament, be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſhall from thenceforth be vtterly voyde and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> that alſo for the reuiuing of dyuers of the ſayd good lawes and ſtatutes, made in the tyme of your ſayd dere father, it may alſo pleaſe your hyghnes, that one acte and Statute, made in the .xxiii. yere of the raigne of the ſayde late kyng Henry the eyght, entituled: An acte that no perſon ſhalbe cyted out of the Dioceſſe where he or ſhe dwelleth, except in certayne caſes. And one other acte made in the .xxiiii. yere of the raigne of the ſayde late kyng, entytuled: An acte that appeales in ſuch caſes as hath ben vſed to be purſued to the ſea of Rome, ſhal not be from henceforth had ne vſed, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme. And one other acte made in the .xxv. yere of the ſayde late Kyng, concernyng reſtraynte of payment of annates and fyrſt fruites of Archbyſſhoprykes, and Byſhoprykes to the ſea of Rome. And one other acte in the ſayde .xxv. yere, entytuled: An acte concernynge the ſubmyſſyon of the cleargy to the kynges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. And alſo one acte made in the ſayde .xxv. yere, entytuled: An acte reſtrayning the payment of annates or fyrſte fruites to the byſſhop of Rome, and of the electyng and conſecratynge of Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſhoppes and byſſhoppes within this realme. And one other acte made in the ſayd .xxv. yere, entytuled: An acte concernyng the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneration of the kinges ſubiectes from exactions and impoſitions heretofore payde to the ſea of Rome, and for hauynge licences and diſpenſations within this realme, without ſuyng further for the ſame. And one other act made in the .xxvi. yere of the ſaid late king entituled. An act for nominacion and conſecration of Suffragans within this realme. And alſo one other act made in the .xxviii. yere of the raigne of the ſayde late kyng, entituled: An act for the releaſe of ſuch as haue obteyned pretended licences and diſpenſations fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sea of Rome, and all and euery braunches, wordes, and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the ſayde ſeuerall actes and ſtatutes, conteyned by aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this preſent parliament, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and at al tymes after the laſt day of this Seſſion of parliament, ſhalbe reuiued, &amp; ſhal ſtand and be in
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:150878:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ful force and ſtrength, to al intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes. And that the braunches, ſentences, and wordes of the ſayd ſeueral actes, and euery of them, from thenceforth ſhal &amp; may be iudged, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; taken to extend to your highnes, your heyres and ſucceſſors as fully and largely as euer the ſame actes or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did extend to the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght your hyghnes father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND THAT</hi> it may alſo pleaſe your hyghnes, that it may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by thaucthoritie of this preſent parliament, that ſo much of one acte or Statute made in the .xxxii. yere of the raigne of your ſayd dere father kyng Henry the eyght entytuled: an Acte concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng precontractes of mariages, and touchyng degrees of conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie, as in the tyme of the late kyng Edward the ſyxte, youre hyghneſſe moſt dere brother, by one other act or Statute was not repealed. And alſo one acte made in the .xxxvii. yere of the raygne of the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, entytuled: an Acte, that Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the Ciuile lawe beyng maryed, may exercyſe eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction, and all and euery braunches and articles in the ſayde two actes laſt mentioned, and not repealed in the tyme of the ſayd late kyng Edward the ſyxt, may from henceforth lykewyſe ſtande and be reuyued, and remayne in theyr full force and ſtrength, to al intentes and purpoſes, any thyng conteyned in the ſayd acte of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale before mentioned; or any other matter or cauſe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> that it may alſo pleaſe your hyghnes that it may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that all other lawes and Statutes, and the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches and clauſes of any act or Statute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed &amp; made voyde by the ſayd acte of repeale, made in the tyme of the late kyng Phyllyp and Quene Mary, and not in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent acte ſpecially mentioned and reuyued, ſhall ſtande, remayne, and be repealed and voyde, in ſuch lyke maner and fourme as they were before the makyng of this acte, any thyng herein conteyned to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND THAT IT</hi> may alſo pleaſe your hyghnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by thauctorite aforeſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one act &amp; ſtatute made in the firſt yere of the raigne of the late kynge Edwarde the ſyxte, your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re brother, entituled: an Acte againſt ſuche perſons as ſhall vnreuerently ſpeake againſt the Sacrament of the bodye and bloud of Chriſte, commonly called the Sacrament of the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and for the receauyng therof vnder bothe kyndes, and all and euery braunches, clauſes, and ſentences therin conteyned, ſhall &amp; may lykewyſe from the laſt day of this Seſſion of parliament, be reuyued, and from thenceforth ſhall and may ſtand, remayne, &amp; be in ful force, ſtrength and effect, to al intentes, conſtructions, &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, in ſuch like maner &amp; fourme, as the ſame was at any tyme
<pb facs="tcp:150878:5"/>
in the firſt yere of the raign of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid late king Edward the ſixt, and law, ſtatute, or other matter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary in any wiſe notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND THAT</hi> alſo it may pleaſe your highnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maye be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſtablyſhed &amp; enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſaid, that one Act and Statute made in the firſt &amp; ſecond yeres of the ſayd late kyng Phyllyp and Quene Mary, entituled: an Acte for the reuyuyng of three ſtatutes made for the puniſhement of hereſies, &amp; alſo the ſaid three ſtatutes mentioned in the ſayd act, &amp; by the ſame acte reuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and all &amp; euery braunches, articles, clauſes, and ſentence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the ſayd ſeueral actes or ſtatutes &amp; euery of them, ſhalbe from the laſt day of this Seſſion of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, demed and remaine vtterly repealed, voyde, and of none effect, to all intentes &amp; purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, any thing in the ſayd ſeuerall actes, or any of them conteyned, or any other matter or cauſe to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> to the intent that all vſurped &amp; forrayne power &amp; auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſpiritual and temporal, may for euer be clearely extinguiſhed and neuer to be vſed or obeyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this Realme, or any other your maieſties dominions or countreys: May it pleaſe your highnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no forrain prince, perſon, prelate, ſtate, or potentate, ſpirituall or temporall, ſhall at any tyme after the laſt day of this Seſſion of parliament, vſe, enioy, or exercyſe any maner of power, iuriſdiction, ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, aucthoritie, preheminence, or priuilege ſpirituall or eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall within this realme, or within any other your maieſties do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minions or countreys that now be or hereafter ſhalbe, but from thenceforth the ſame ſhalbe clearely abolyſhed out of this realme, and all other your hyghnes dominions for euer, any ſtatute, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, cuſtome, conſtitutions, or any other matter or cauſe what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> that alſo it may likewyſe pleaſe your highnes, that it may be eſtablyſhed &amp; enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that ſuch iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, priuileges, ſuperiorities, and preheminences ſpiritual &amp; eccleſiaſticall, as by any ſpiritual or eccleſiaſtical power or auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie hath heretofore ben, or may lawfully be exercyſed or vſed, for the viſitacion of the eccleſiaſticall State and perſons, and for reformation, order, and correction of the ſame, and of all maner errours, hereſies, ſciſmes, abuſes, offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, contemptes, and enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhall for euer by aucthoritie of this preſent parliament, bee vnited and annexed to the imperiall Crowne of this Realme. And that your hyghnes, your heyres &amp; ſucceſſours, kinges or quenes of this realme, ſhal haue ful power &amp; aucthorite by vertue of this act by letters patentes, vnder the great ſeale of Englande, to aſſigne, name, &amp; aucthoriſe, when and as often as your hygneſſe, your hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res or ſucceſſours ſhall thinke mete and conuenient, &amp; for ſuch and
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:150878:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo long tyme as ſhal pleaſe your hyghnes, your heires or ſucceſſors ſuch perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s beyng natural borne ſubiectes to your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, your heires, or ſucceſſours, as your maieſtie, your heires or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours ſhal thinke mete to exerciſe, vſe, occupy, and execute vnder your hyghnes, your heyres and ſucceſſours, all maner of iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, priuileges, and preheminences in any wyſe touching or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction within theſe your realmes of Englande and Irelande, or any other your hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dominions or countreys, and to viſite, reforme, redreſſe, order, correct and amend al ſuch errours, hereſies, ſciſmes, abuſes, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, contemptes, and enormities whatſoeuer, which by any maner ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall power, aucthoritie, or iuriſdiction, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or may lawfully be reformed, ordred, redreſſed, corrected, reſtrayned or amended, to the pleaſure of almyghty God, thencreaſe of vertue, &amp; the conſeruacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the peace &amp; vnitie of this realme. And that ſuch perſon or perſons ſo to be named, aſſigned, aucthoriſed, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by your hyghnes, your heyres or ſucceſſours, after the ſayd let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes to hym or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made &amp; deliuered as is aforeſayd, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this act &amp; of the ſaid letters patents vnder your hyghnes, your heyres or ſucceſſours, to exercyſe, vſe, and execute all the premiſſes, accordyng to the tenour and effecte of the ſayd letters patentes. Any matter or cauſe to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> for the better obſeruacion and maintenaunce of this act, may it pleaſe your hyghnes that it may be further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that al and euery Archebyſhop, Byſhop, and all and euery other eccleſiaſticall perſon, and other eccleſiaſticall officer and miniſter, of what eſtate, dignitie, prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or degree ſoeuer he or they be or ſhalbe, and all and euery temporall Iudge, Iuſticer, Mayre, and other lay or temporall offycer and miniſter, and euery other perſone, hauynge your hyghneſſe fee or wages within this Realme, or anye youre hyghneſſe dominions, ſhall make, take, and receaue, a corporall othe vpon the Euangeliſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch perſon or perſonnes as ſhall pleaſe your hyghneſſe, your heyres or ſucceſſours, vnder the greate Seale of Englande, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſygne and name, to accepte and take the ſame, accordynge to the tenoure and effecte hereafter folowyng. That is to ſay:</p>
            <p>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do vtterly teſtyfie &amp; declare in my conſcience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Quenes hyghneſſe is the onely Supreame gouernoure of this Realme, and of all other her hyghneſſe domynyons and countreyes, aſwell in all ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall thynges or cauſes: as temporall, &amp; that no forrayne prynce, perſon, prelate, ſtate, or potentate, hath or ought to haue any iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, power, ſuperioritie, prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or aucthorite eccleſiaſtical or ſpiritual within this realme, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:150878:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
I do vtterly remounce &amp; forſake all forraine iuriſdictions, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, ſuperiorities, &amp; aucthorities, and do promyſe that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth I ſhall beare fayth &amp; trewe allegiaunce to the Quenes high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, her heyres and lawful ſucceſſours, and to my power ſhal aſſiſt and defend all iuriſdictions, priuileges, preheminences, &amp; auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities graunted or belonging to the Quenes highneſſe, her heyres and ſucceſſours, or vnited and annexed to thimperiall Crowne of this realme, ſo helpe me God, and the contentes of this booke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> that it may be alſo enacted, that yf any ſuch archbyſhop, byſhop, or any other Eccleſiaſticall officer or miniſter, or any of the ſayd temporall iudges, iuſticiaries, or other lay officer or miniſter, ſhall peremptoryly or obſtinately refuſe to take or receaue the ſayd other: That then he ſo refuſyng, ſhall forfeyt and loſe onely duryng his lyfe, all &amp; euery Eccleſiaſticall and Spirituall promotion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice &amp; office, and euery temporall and lay promotion and office, which he hath ſoly at the tyme of ſuch refuſall made, and that the whole tytle, interreſt, and incumbencye in euery ſuch promotion, benefice, and other office, as agaynſt ſuch perſon only ſo refuſing, duryng his lyfe, ſhall clearely ceaſe, &amp; be voyde, as though the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſo refuſyng were dead. And that alſo all and euery ſuch perſon and perſons ſo refuſyng to take the ſayd othe, ſhall immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch refuſall, be from thenſforth duryng his lyfe diſabled to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne or exercyſe anye office, or other promotion, whiche he at the tyme of ſuch refuſall hath ioyntly or in common with anye other perſon or perſons. And that al and euery perſon and perſons that at any time hereafter ſhalbe preferred, promoted, or collated to any Archebyſſhopryke, or Byſſhopryke, or to any other ſpirituall or ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical benefice, promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dignitie, office, or miniſtery, or that ſhalbe by your hyghneſſe, your heyres, or ſucceſſours, preferred or promoted to any temporal or lay office, miniſtery, or ſeruice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this realme, or in any your hyghnes dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, before he or they ſhall take vpon him or them to receaue, vſe, exerciſe, ſupplye, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy any ſuch archebyſhoprike, byſhoprike, promotion, dignitie, office, miniſtery or ſeruice, ſhall likewiſe make, take, &amp; receaue the ſaid corporal othe before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euangeliſt, before ſuch perſons as haue or ſhall haue aucthoritie to admitte any ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any ſuch office, miniſtery, or ſeruice, or els before ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons as by your highnes, your heyres or ſucceſſours by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the great ſeale of England, ſhalbe named, aſſigned or appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to miniſter the ſaid oth. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may likewiſe be further enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any ſuch perſon or perſons as at any tyme hereafter ſhalbe promoted, preferred, or collated to any ſuch promotion ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall benefyce, offyce, or miniſtery, or that by your highnes, your heires or ſucceſſors, ſhalbe
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:150878:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
promoted or preferred to any temporall or laye office, miniſtery, or ſeruice, ſhall and do peremtorilye and obſtinately refuſe to take the ſame othe ſo to hym to be offred, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he or they ſo refuſing, ſhal preſently be iudged diſabled in the law, to receaue, take, or haue the ſame promotion Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical, the ſame temporal of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyce, myniſtery, or ſeruice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this realme, or any other your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dominions, to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND THAT</hi> it maye be further enacted by thaucthoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde, that all and euery perſon and perſons Temporall, ſuyng ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, or <hi>Ouſtre le mayne,</hi> out of the handes of your hyghneſſe, your hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or ſucceſſours, before his or theyr liuery or <hi>Ouſtre le maine</hi> ſued forth and allowed, and euery Temporall perſon or perſons, doyng anye homage to your hyghneſſe, your heyres or ſucceſſours, or that ſhall be receyued into ſeruice with your hyghnes, your heyres or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, ſhall make, take, and receiue the ſayde corporall othe before mentioned, before the Lorde Chauncellour of England, or the lord keper of the greate ſeale for the tyme beyng, or before ſuch perſone or perſons as by your hyghnes, your heyres or ſucceſſoures ſhal be named and appoynted to accepte or receaue the ſame. And that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all and euery perſon and perſons takyng orders, and all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other perſon and perſons, which ſhalbe promoted or preferred to any degree of learnynge in anye vniuerſitie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this your realme or dominions, before he ſhall receaue or take any ſuch orders, or be preferred to any ſuch degree of learnyng, ſhall make, take, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaue the ſayde othe by this acte ſette forthe and declared as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, before hys or theyr Ordynary, Commiſſarye, Chauncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, or vicechauncellour, or theyr ſufficient deputyes in the ſayde vniuerſitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, &amp; that it may be further enacted by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie aforeſayd, that if any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing any eſtate of inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in any temporall office or offices, ſhall hereafter obſtinately and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptoryly refuſe to accept and take the ſayd othe as is aforeſayd, and after at any tyme duryng his lyfe, ſhall wyllyngly requyre to take &amp; receaue the ſaid oth, and ſo do take &amp; accept the ſame othe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anye perſon or perſonnes that ſhall haue lawfull aucthoritie to miniſter the ſame: That then euery ſuch perſon immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath ſo receaued the ſame othe, ſhalbe veſted, iudged, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in lyke eſtate and poſſeſſion of the ſayd offyce, as he was before the ſayd refuſall, &amp; ſhall and may vſe and exerciſe the ſayd offyce, in ſuch maner &amp; fourme as he ſhould or myght haue done before ſuche refuſall, any thyng in this acte conteyned to the contrarye in anye wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND FOR THE MORE</hi> ſure obſeruation of this acte, and the vtter extinguyſhement of al forraine &amp; vſurped power &amp; aucthorite
<pb facs="tcp:150878:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may it pleaſe your hyghnes that it may be further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any perſon or perſons, dwelling or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habytyng within this your Realme, or in any other your hyghnes Realmes or dominions, of what eſtate, dignitie, or degree ſoeuer he or they be, after thend of .xxx. dayes next after the determinacion of this ſeſſion of this preſent parliament, ſhal by wrytinge, printing, teaching, preaching, expreſſe wordes, dede or act, aduiſedly, malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, &amp; directly affirme, hold, ſtande with, ſet forth, maintayne, or defende thaucthoritie, preheminence, power, or iuriſdiction Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall or Eccleſiaſticall of any forreyne Prynce, Prelate, Perſon, State, or Potentate, whatſoeuer heretofore claymed, vſed, or vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped within this Realme, or any dominion or countrey being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or vnder the power, domynyon, or obeyſaunce of your hyghnes, or ſhall aduyſedly, maliciouſly, and directely put in vre or execute any thyng for thextollyng, aduauncement, ſettyng forth, mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce or defence of any ſuch pretended or vſurped iuriſdiction, power, preheminence or aucthoritie, or any part therof: That then euery ſuch perſon and perſons ſo doyng and offending, theyr abbet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, aydours, procurers, and counſaylours, beyng thereof law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conuicted and attaynted accordyng to the due order &amp; courſe of the commen lawes of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ealme, for this or theyr fyrſt offence ſhall forfeyte and loſe vnto your hyghneſſe, your heyres and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, all his and theyr goodes and cattelles, aſwell reall as perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. And yf any ſuche perſon ſo conuicted or attaynted ſhall not haue or be worth of his proper goodes and cattelles to the value of xx. li. at the tyme of ſuch his conuiction or atteyndour: that then euery ſuch perſon ſo conuicted &amp; atteynted, ouer &amp; beſydes the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of all his ſaid goodes &amp; cattelles, ſhal haue and ſuffer impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the ſpace of one whole yere without bayle or mainpriſe. And that alſo all and euery the benefyces, prebendes, and other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall promocions and dignities, whatſoeuer of euery Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall perſon ſo offendyng and beyng atteynted ſhall immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch atteyndour, be vtterly voyde to all intentes and purpoſes as though thincumbent therof were dead. And that the patron &amp; donour of euery ſuch benefice, prebend, ſpiritual promocion &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſhall &amp; may lawfully preſent vnto the ſame, or giue the ſame in ſuche maner and fourme as yf the ſayde incumbent were deade. And yf any ſuch offendour or offendours after ſuche conuiction or atteyndour do eftſones committe or do the ſayde offences or any of them in maner and fourme aforeſayde, and be therof duely conuic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and atteynted as is aforeſayd: That then euery ſuch offendour and offendours ſhall for the ſame ſeconde offence incurre into the daungers, penalties, and forfeytures ordeyned and prouided by the Statute of prouiſion and Preminire, made in the .xvi. yere of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150878:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reigne of Kynge Rycharde the ſeconde. And if anye ſuche offendour or offendoures, at anye tyme after the ſayde ſeconde conuiction and attayndoure, doo the thirde tyme commytte and doo the ſayd offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or anye of them, in maner and fourme aforeſayde, and be therof duelye conuicted and attaynted as is aforeſayde: That then euerye ſuch offence or offences ſhall be demed and adiudged highe treaſon, and that thoffendour and offendours therein, beynge thereof lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye conuycted and attaynted, accordynge to the lawes of thys Realme, ſhall ſuffer paynes of deathe, and other penalties, forfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and loſſes, as in caſes of hyghe treaſon by the lawes of thys Realme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND ALSO THAT IT MAY</hi> lykewyſe pleaſe youre hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that it may be enacted by thauctoritie aforeſaide, that no maner of perſon or perſones, ſhalbe moleſted or impeached for any thoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforeſaid, committed or perpretated only by preaching, teachyng or wordes, onles he or they be therof lawfullye endicted, within the ſpace of one half yeare next after his or their offences ſo commytted And in caſe any perſon or perſons ſhall fortune to be impriſoned for anye of the ſayde offences commytted by preachyng, teachynge, or woordes onelye, and be not thereof indicted wythin the ſpace of one halfe yeare nexte after hys or theyr ſuch offence ſoo commytted and done: That then the ſayde perſonne ſoo impryſoned ſhall be ſet at lybertye, and be no lenger deteyned in priſon for anye ſuche cauſe or offence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED ALVVAIES AND BE IT</hi> enacted by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye aforeſayde, that thys acte or anye thing therein conteyned ſhal not in any wiſe extend to repeale, any clauſe, matter, or ſentence conteyned or ſpecified, in the ſaid Acte of Repeale, made in the ſayde fyrſt and ſeconde yeares of the raignes of the ſayde late king Philip and Quene Mary, as doth in any wiſe touch or concerne any mater or caſe of preminire, or that doth make or ordeine any mater or cauſe to be within the caſe of preminire, but that the ſame, forſomuch only as toucheth or concerneth any caſe or matter of preminire ſhal ſtand and remayne in ſuch force and effect as the ſame was before the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge of this acte. Any thinge in thys acte, conteined to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye in anye wyſe notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED ALSO AND BE IT</hi> enacted by thaucthorytye aforeſayde, that thys acte or anye thynge therein contayned ſhall not in any wiſe extende or be preiudycial to any perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for
<pb facs="tcp:150878:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any offence or offences committed or done, or hereafter to be commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted or done, contrary to the tenour and effect of any acte or Statute now reuiued by this acte, before thend of xxx. daies next after thend of the ſeſſion of this preſent parliament, any thing in this act contei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, or any other matter or cauſe to the contrary notwithſtandyng. And if it happen that any pere of this Realme ſhal fortune to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted of, and for anye offence that is reuiued or made preminire or treaſon by this act, that then he ſo being indicted ſhal haue his trial by his peres, in ſuch like maner and forme, as in other caſes of trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon hath bene vſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED ALVVAIES</hi> and be it enacted as is aforeſayde, that no maner of order, acte or determination, for any matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or cauſe Eccleſiaſticall, had or made by thauctoritie of this preſent parliament, ſhalbe accepted, demed, interpretate or adiudged at any tyme hereafter, to be any errour, hereſy, ſciſme, or ſciſmaticall opinion: Any order, decree, ſentence, conſtitution, or lawe, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſame be to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED ALVVAIES AND BE</hi> it enacted by thauctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aforeſaid. That ſuch perſon or perſons to whome your highnes your heires or Succeſſours, ſhall hereafter by letters patentes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great Seale of England, geue aucthority to haue or execute any iuriſdiction, power or aucthoritie Spiritual, or to viſit, reforme order, or corect any errours, hereſyes, ſcyſmes, abuſes or enormities by vertue of this Act, ſhall not in any wiſe haue aucthority or power to order, determyne, or adiudge anye matter or cauſe to be hereſye, but only ſuche as heretofore haue ben determined, ordred, or adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be hereſy by thaucthority of the canonical Scryptures, or by the firſt four general Counſailes, or any of them, or by any other ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neral Counſaile wherin the ſame was declared hereſy, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> expreſſe and plaine wordes of the ſaid canonical Scriptures, or ſuch as here after ſhalbe ordred, iudged, or determyned to be hereſy, by the hyghe Court of Parliament of this Realme, with thaſſent of the Cleargy in their conuocation. Any thyng in this act conteyned to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND BE IT FVRTHER</hi> enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſaied, that no perſon or perſons, ſhalbe hereafter endicted or arraigned for any the offences, made, ordeyned, reuiued, or adiudged by thys acte, onleſſe ther be two ſufficient witneſſes or more, to teſtify and declare the ſaid offences, wherof he ſhalbe indicted or arrained. And that the ſayd witneſſes, or ſo many of them as ſhalbe liuing, and within this Realme at the time of the arraygnemente of ſuch perſon ſo indicted ſhalbe brought forth in perſon, face to face, before the party ſo array<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and there ſhal teſtify and declare what they can ſay againſt the
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:150878:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
partie ſo arraygned, yf he require the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED ALSO</hi> and be it further enacted by thaucthority aforeſaid, that if any perſon or perſons ſhal hereafter happen to geue any reliefe, ayd, or comfort, or in any wyſe be aiding, helping, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting to the perſon or perſons of any that ſhall hereafter happen to be an offendour in any mater or caſe of Preminire or treaſon reuiued or made by this acte: That then ſuche reliefe, ayde, or comforte giuen ſhall not be iudged or taken to be any offence, onleſſe ther be two ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient witneſſes at the leaſt, that can and will openly teſtify and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that the perſon or perſons that ſo gaue ſuch reliefe, ayde, or com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte, had notice and knowledge of ſuch offence, committed and done by the ſayde offendour, at the tyme of ſuch reliefe, ayde, or comforte ſo to him giuen or miniſtred: any thinge in this acte conteyned, or anye other matter or cauſe to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND VVHERE ONE PRETENSID</hi> ſentence hathe hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hene giuen in the conſiſtory in Powles before certaine Iudges <hi>Delegate,</hi> by the authoritie <hi>Legantine,</hi> of the late cardinal Poole, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a forreyne vſurped power and aucthoritie agaynſte Rycharde Chetwod Eſquier, and Agnes his wife, by the name of Agnes Wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, at the ſute of Charles Tyrrel gentleman, in a cauſe of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſolemnized betwene the ſaid Richard and Agnes, as by the ſame pretenſed ſentence more playnly doth appeare. From which ſentence the ſayde Rychard and Agnes haue appealed to the courte of Rome, which appeale doth there remayne, and yet is not determined. Maye it therfore pleaſe your hyghnes that it may be enacted by the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforeſaid, that if ſentence in the ſaid appeale, ſhal happen to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at the ſayde courte of Rome, for and in the behalfe of the ſaid Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard and Agnes, for the reuerſyng of the ſayd pretenſid ſentence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ende of thre ſcore dayes next after the end of this Seſſion of this preſent Parliament: That then the ſame ſhalbe iudged &amp; taken to be good and effectuall in the lawe, and ſhal, and maye be vſed, ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and allowed in anye courte or place wythin thys Realme, anye thing in this acte, or in any other acte or ſtatute, conteined to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding. And if no ſentence ſhalbe giuen at the courte of Rome, in the ſaid appeale for the reuerſing of the ſaid pretenſid ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence before thy ende of the ſayde three ſcore dayes, that then it ſhall and maye, be lawfull for the ſayde Rycharde, and Agnes, and either of them at anye tyme herafter to commenſe, take, ſue, and proſecute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid appeale from the ſaide pretenſed ſentence, and for the reuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing of the ſaide pretenſed ſentence within this Realme, in ſuche lyke maner and forme as was vſed to be purſued or mighte haue ben pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued within this realme, at any tyme ſince the .xxiiii. yere of the reigne of the ſayde late kyng Henry the eyght, vpon ſentences geuen in the
<pb facs="tcp:150878:9"/>
court or courtes of any Archbiſhop within this realme. And that ſuch appeale as ſo hereafter ſhalbe taken or purſued by the ſayde Richard Chetwod and Agnes, or either of them, and the ſentence that herein or therevpon ſhal hereafter be geuen, ſhalbe iudged to be good and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectuall in the lawe, to all intentes and purpoſes: anye lawe, cuſtome vſage, canon, conſtitution or any other matter or cauſe to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVIDED ALSO AND BE IT</hi> enacted by thaucthorytye aforeſayde, that wher there is the like appeale now depending in the ſayd court of Rome, betwene one Robert Harcourt, Merchaunt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaple, and Elizabeth Harcourt, otherwiſe called Elizabeth Robins of the one partie: And Anthony Fydell Marchaunt Straunger, on thother partie, that the ſayd Roberte, Elizabeth, and Anthonye, and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhal and may for the proſecuting and trieng of their ſaid appeale, haue and enioy the like remedy, benefitte, and aduantage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like maner and fourme as the ſaid Richard and Agnes, or any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath, may, or ought to haue and enioy, this act or anye thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> conteyned to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
